Finding Aid for the June in Buffalo Papers, 1975-1977, 1980
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
June in Buffalo Papers, 1975-1977, 1980
Mus. Arc. 34
Feldman, Morton, 1926-1987
1 box (34 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The June in Buffalo Papers consist of administrative papers created to run the music festival that ran 1975-1978, and 1980 at the State University of New York at Buffalo and clippings about the concerts.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Originally received with Morton Feldman Papers, which were a gift of Barbara Monk Feldman in 1992.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
The June in Buffalo festival of contemporary music was established by Morton Feldman in 1975. Morton Feldman joined the University at Buffalo Music Faculty in 1972. He was the Slee Professor, 1972-1973, Edgar Varèse Professor, 1975-1987, and the Director of the Center of the Creative and Performing Arts, 1976-1980. Feldman established the June in Buffalo festival in 1975 as a counterpart to the Center of the Creative and Performing Arts' successful Evenings for New Music concerts. The new festival was presented 1975-1978, and again in 1980, with a year off in 1979 when Feldman was on sabbatical. The festival was revived in 1986 by composer David Felder and is still in operation as of this writing (2015). Although the two festivals share the same name it is convenient to consider them as two separate entities.
In addition to presenting concerts, Feldman's festival created a seminar environment in which student composers attended workshops where distinguished composers-in-residence rehearsed their works and gave lectures. Feldman also wanted to create a more intense listening experience by presenting programs that contained multiple works by a single composer. To that end, twelve works by John Cage were presented on the three concerts that opened the first festival in June 1975. Other single-composer programs were devoted to the works of Christian Wolff, Ralph Shapey, George Crumb, Lejaren Hiller, Nils Vigeland, Steve Reich, Charles Wuorinen, Henry Brant, Elliott Carter, Stefan Wolpe, Milton Babbitt, Lou Harrison, Earle Brown, and Aaron Copland. Works by earlier twentieth-century composers, including Ives, Schoenberg, Satie, Cowell, Webern, Berg, and Bártók were also presented on June in Buffalo programs. Three works received their United States premieres and five works received their world premieres at the festival. All concerts but one were held in what was then called Baird Hall (now Allen Hall) on what is now the South Campus of the University at Buffalo. The June 1, 1976 concert was held at the Albright-Knox Art Gallery in Buffalo.
Scope and Content Note
The June in Buffalo Papers consist of administrative papers created to run the music festival at the State University of New York at Buffalo, including schedules, budgets, correspondence, programs and publicity materials, as well as clippings about the concerts. The records are incomplete, containing content for 1975, 1976, 1977, and 1980, but none for 1978.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series for each of the four years of records held. Materials are categorized by the year of the festival to which they pertain not necessarily by the date of creation. However, the date of creation is stated in the inventory. Concert reviews are organized by date of the concert reviewed, not by publication date. The series are subdivided when appropriate by subseries for Administrative papers, including budgetary documents, Publicity and Programs, Correspondence, and Clippings.
I. 1975
II. 1976
III. 1977
IV. 1980
Container List
- June in Buffalo papers, 1975, I.; Folder 1-10
  Arranged into subseries for:
  I.A Administrative papers
  I.B Correspondence
  I.C Clippings
  - Administrative papers 1975, I.A; Folder 1
    - Typescript note from Renée Levine and Jan Williams to Morton Feldman and Lejaren Hiller with performance budget, April 25, 1975, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1975, I.B; Folder 2-4
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Letter from Sylvia Brigham-Dimiziani to Christian Wolff, November 13, 1974, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter from John Duffy (for Meet the Composer) to Morton Feldman, April 28, 1975, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter from Mimi Johnson (for John Cage) to Sylvia Brigham-Dimiziani, November 4, 1974, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1975, I.C; Folder 5-10
    Arranged chronologically by the date of the concert (not the date of publication of the review).
    - June 2, 1975 concert review by Jeff Simon in Buffalo Evening News, June 3, 1975?, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - June 6, 1975 concert review by Jeff Simon in Buffalo Evening News, June 7, 1975?, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - June 16, 1975 concert review by John Dwyer in Buffalo Evening News, June 17, 1975, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - June 17, 1975 concert review by Thomas Putnam in Buffalo Courier-Express, June 18, 1975?, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - June 18, 1975 concert review by Jeff Simon in Buffalo Evening News, June 19, 1975?, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - June 20, 1975 concert review by Jeff Simon in Buffalo Evening News, June 21, 1975?, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 10)
- June in Buffalo papers, 1976, II.; Folder 11-29
  II.A Administrative papers
  II.B Correspondence
  II.C Publicity and programs
  II.D Clippings
  - Administrative papers, 1976, II.A; Folder 11
    - Schedules, ticket activity, and expenses, July 15, 1976, undated, 10 leaves (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976, II.B; Folder 12-15
    - Letters (2) from John Duffy (for Meet the composer) to Morton Feldman, August 21, 1975, December 15, 1975, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letter from George Levine to Morton Feldman, November 3, 1975, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters (2) from William Thomson to Morton Feldman, February 17, 1976, June 21, 1976, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters (2) from William K. Wachob (for William Thomson) to composers George Crumb and Steve Reich, March 4, 1976, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Publicity and programs, 1976, II.C; Folder 16
    - Programs, news announcement, and poster for June in Buffalo, 1976, 4 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1976, II.D; Folder 17-29
    - Four articles about the entire June in Buffalo Festival, May 26-June 18, 1976, 4 leaves (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Two reviews of June 1, 1976 concert, June 2, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Buffalo Courier-Express review by Thomas Putnam
      Buffalo Evening News review by Jeff Simon
    - Two reviews of June 2, 1976 concert, June 3, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Buffalo Evening News review by Herman Trotter
    - Two reviews of June 3, 1976 concert, June 4, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Buffalo Evening News review by John Dwyer
    - Two reviews of June 1, 1976 concert, June 5, 1976, 2 articles photocopied on 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - June 7, 1976 concert review by John Dwyer in Buffalo Evening News, June 8, 1976, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Two reviews of June 8, 1976 concert, June 9, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - June 9, 1976 concert review by Herman Trotter in Buffalo Evening News, June 10, 1976, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - June 10, 1976 concert review by Herman Trotter in Buffalo Evening News, June 11, 1976, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Two reviews of June 11, 1976 concert, June 12, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Two reviews of June 14, 1976 concert, June 15, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Two reviews of June 16, 1976 concert, June 17, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Two reviews of June 18, 1976 concert, June 19, 1976, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 29)
- June in Buffalo papers, 1977, III.; Folder 30-32
  III.A Correspondence
  III.B Programs
  - Correspondence, 1976, III.A; Folder 30-31
    - Manuscript drafts of letters from Morton Feldman to Milton Babbitt and Jacob Druckman, undated, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Letter from Suzanne Stephens (for Karlheinz Stockhausen) to Morton Feldman, November 6, 1976, 1 typescript leaf (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Programs, 1977, III.B; Folder 32
    - Folded pamphlet of programs for entire June in Buffalo festival, 1977, 1 folded leaf (Box 1, Folder 32)
- June in Buffalo papers, 1980, IV.; Folder 33-34
  IV.A Administrative papers
  IV.B Correspondence
  - Administrative papers 1980, IV.A; Folder 33
    - Schedules, expenses, and handwritten notes about June in Buffalo, 1980, 27 leaves and 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1980, IV.B; Folder 34
    - Five letters from John Duffy (for Meet the Composer) to Morton Feldman, January 31, 1980, February 1, 1980, 11 leaves; The letters concern appearances at June in Buffalo 1980 by composers George Crumb, Steve Reich, Ralph Shapey, Christian Wolff, and Charles Wuorinen. Each letter is accompanied by a contract. (Box 1, Folder 34)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Department
Subjects
Music festivals--New York (State)--Buffalo; June in Buffalo (Festival) (1975-1980: Buffalo, N.Y.)
Genres
Clippings; Administrative records
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Recordings of June in Buffalo, 1975-1978, 1980
Mus. Arc. 30
The collection contains recordings of fifty-one of the fifty-three concerts presented at the previous hit June in Buffalo next hit festival from 1975-1978 and in 1980. Approximately 216 works were recorded as well as some spoken introductions to works by their respective composers.